Ladies and gentlemen, gather around.
سيداتي سادتي، اجتمعوا .
I would love to share with you a story.
أود أن أشارككم قصة.
Once upon a time
كان يا ما كان
in 19th century Germany,
في ألمانيا القرن ال19،
there was the book.
كان هناك الكتاب.
Now during this time,
الآن في تلك الأثناء،
the book was the king of storytelling.
كان الكتاب هو ملك سرد القصص.
It was venerable.
كان مهيبا.
It was ubiquitous.
كان موجودا في كل مكان.
But it was a little bit boring.
لكنه كان مملا نوعا ما.
Because in its 400 years of existence,
لأنه خلال 400 سنة من وجوده،
storytellers never evolved the book
لم يطور القصاصون الكتاب أبدا
as a storytelling device.
كجهاز لسرد القصص.
But then one author arrived,
لكن كاتبا قد جاء،
and he changed the game forever.
وغير اللعبة إلى الأبد.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
His name was Lothar,
اسمه كان لوثار،
Lothar Meggendorfer.
لوثار ميجيندورفر.
Lothar Meggendorfer put his foot down,
وضع لوثار ميجيندورفر قدمه أرضا،
and he said, "Genug ist genug!"
وقال، "Genug ist genug!"
He grabbed his pen,
أمسك بقلمه،
he snatched his scissors.
وانتزع مقصه.
This man refused to fold to the conventions of normalcy
رفض هذا الرجل أن يرضخ لما يعتبر عاديا
and just decided to fold.
وقرر أن يغير.
History would know Lothar Meggendorfer
سيعرف التاريخ لوثار ميجيندورفر
as -- who else? --
ك -- من غيره؟ --
the world's first true inventor
أول مخترع حقيقي في العالم
of the children's pop-up book.
للكتاب المنبثق للأطفال.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
For this delight and for this wonder,
لهذه المتعة وهذا السحر،
people rejoiced.
ابتهج الناس.
(Cheering)
(هتاف)
They were happy because the story survived,
كانوا سعداء لأن القصة نجت،
and that the world would keep on spinning.
وأن العالم سيستمر في الدوران.
Lothar Meggendorfer wasn't the first
لوثار ميجيندورفر لم يكن أول
to evolve the way a story was told,
من طور طريقة سرد القصص،
and he certainly wasn't the last.
وهو بالتأكيد لم يكن الأخير.
Whether storytellers realized it or not,
سواء أدرك القصاصون ذلك أم لا،
they were channeling Meggendorfer's spirit
كانوا يتحدون روح ميجيندورفر
when they moved opera to vaudville,
حين نقلو الأوبرا إلى مسرحية هزلية،
radio news to radio theater,
أخبار الراديو إلى مسرح الراديو،
film to film in motion
الفيلم إلى فيلم متحرك
to film in sound, color, 3D,
إلى فيلم بصوت، بألوان، ثلاثي الأبعاد،
on VHS and on DVD.
على VHS وعلى DVD.
There seemed to be no cure for this Meggendorferitis.
يبدو أنه ليس هناك علاج لهذه الميجيندورفريات.
And things got a lot more fun when the Internet came around.
وأصبحت الأمور أكثر إمتاعا بمجيء الانترنت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Because, not only could people broadcast their stories throughout the world,
لأنه، ليس فقط بإمكان الناس إذاعة قصصهم عبر العالم،
but they could do so
لكن يمكنهم كذلك القيام بذلك
using what seemed to be an infinite amount of devices.
باستخدام ما يبدو أنه كم هائل من الأجهزة.
For example, one company
على سبيل المثال، إحدى الشركات
would tell a story of love
ستسرد قصة الحب
through its very own search engine.
عن طريق محرك البحث الخاص بها.
One Taiwanese production studio
أحد استوديوهات الانتاج التايوانية
would interpret American politics in 3D.
ستترجم السياسة الأمريكية إلى ثلاثية أبعاد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And one man would tell the stories of his father
وأحد الأشخاص سيسرد قصص والده
by using a platform called Twitter
باستخدام منصة تدعى تويتر
to communicate the excrement his father would gesticulate.
لإيصال التفاهات التي يقدم عليها والده.
And after all this, everyone paused;
وبعد كل هذا، توقف الجميع؛
they took a step back.
خطوا إلى الوراء.
They realized that, in 6,000 years of storytelling,
أدركوا أنه خلال 6000 سنة من سرد القصص،
they've gone from depicting hunting on cave walls
انتقلوا من وصف القنص على جدران الكهف
to depicting Shakespeare on Facebook walls.
إلى وصف شكسبير على جدران الفيسبوك.
And this was a cause for celebration.
وهذا كان سببا للاحتفال.
The art of storytelling has remained unchanged.
فن سرد القصص بقي ثابتا.
And for the most part, the stories are recycled.
والجزء الأهم، أن القصص تمت إعادة تدويرها.
But the way that humans tell the stories
لكن الطريقة التي يسرد بها الناس القصص
has always evolved
قد تطورت دائما
with pure, consistent novelty.
بحداثة خالصة ومتسقة.
And they remembered a man,
وتذكروا رجلا،
one amazing German,
ألمانيا مدهشا،
every time a new storytelling device
في كل مرة يظهر جهاز جديد
popped up next.
لسرد القصص.
And for that,
ولهذا،
the audience --
الجمهور --
the lovely, beautiful audience --
الجمهور الرائع والجميل --
would live happily ever after.
سيعيش في سعادة أبدية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)